the idea cafe now I want to explain it
without using the word idea the idea of
the idea cafe braid won't cope with
another word is that eventually it's
going to be its own platform where
anyone can come on ask the question find
someone pick a time and other people
will
well join as well and everyone will get
to experience a conversation where
they're seen and heard on a topic that
matters to them and I'm hoping that it
isn't this what is currently on all the
social media platforms this trolling
this debate instead of connection and
that just that just having a place for
humanity to connect helps improve the
worlds in a big way and then I have huge
plans going from that once we get that
platform going but that's that's plenty
number number one so thank you all for
joining me today's question because we
round a question is how has your autism
diagnosis impacted your life we each
take up to 5 minutes so I'll kind of
like flash 5 on the screen when you've
gotten to 5 minutes
ish and then you can finish up your
thought and then or if you're done
before that you are absolutely welcome
to be done before that and then we will
kind of have a brief open discussion for
the remainder of the house an hour after
that was done and I'll mute the other
two people that aren't speaking during
the five minutes so would anyone like to
start well for me it's it's really
bright so I'm sort of self diagnosed um
I I did have a therapist I saw as a
teenager who had written down that I was
probably on the spectrum but that was
never followed through those my mum I
guess either didn't think to ask what
was going on or knew and then took me
out of therapy and just didn't tell me
so that was a that was I guess when I
could have found out 20 years ago um but
then I I got a career working in the
field of autism work in schools and I
realized probably about four or five
years ago that I was connecting better
to the students they worked with then my
my co-workers like who that's
interesting
being in the field I also knew what the
current DSM at the time said for
diagnostic stuff and I was like well I
don't that um but then as I did more
research because that's what I do I
discovered that that what their I
unfortunately is called the female
phenotype I don't really like that name
but it fit me so well and so I actually
went back to the therapist ahead as a
teenager and I was like hey these is
going on and she's like yeah well
actually wrote that down 20 years ago
okay and I mentioned it to some
co-workers who'd been in the field and
one of my friends who's been an autism
support worker for like 25 years I
messaged her and I was like you think he
might be autistic and her response was
to laugh in the friendliest of ways and
say yeah of course you are so that's
that's how I found out and when I found
that out and kind of came to terms with
that I realized that it gave me two
things that I really didn't have before
it gave me a reason for so much of what
had been going on a reason why I had
felt so different and they tell kids all
the time you all feel different it's
totally normal but it's different when
you are different and the world treats
you like you're drastically different it
is not the same as a kid who feels
different um and it didn't matter what I
did I was always out of groups I was
always not quite fitting I was it just
wasn't a place for me in the world um
and I was a bigger target for abuse and
bullying than a lot of the people around
me even as an adult I could be in a room
and if there's an abuser or a bully in
the room almost always I will be the
first one they target whether they know
me or not and it's taken a long time to
understand that it's because I'm
different and when you're different you
can unearth and when people there police
the people who are different are the
people they'll attack first often so
having that um the reason has really
helped me feel just better about it and
like there's somewhere I can do with
something you can do with this somewhere
I can go with this I'm not just sitting
there floundering around going um and
part of that is that it's brought a
community I never felt like I fit
anywhere in my family with friends with
anywhere and until this and I joined
Facebook groups and I talked to people
like you guys and I realized that there
is a whole lot of people in the world
very much like me
who communicate like me who understand
things like me who I can feel safe being
me with which is very very rare for me
and these people have brought support
some of the most compassionate people in
the world and we share knowledge and we
share ideas um and it's people who I
just feel very safe with which for me
feeling safe with people is very
difficult things uh vines um and one of
the things is I think because we have a
bit of a different language we might
speak English just like my family speaks
English but I speak it differently I use
it differently and that's not often
understood um and there's like a quote
I've been reading I don't know where you
guys live I live in Canada and we're
going through an election process right
now so I read up on the different
parties all of them you know hoots to be
fair but one of them has written a book
recently and there's a quote in it that
I thought really fit with how I work
language and he said of it's dead meet
Doug meet Singh who's in the NDP party
and he said I truly believe you can
never fully connect to someone unless
you speak the language they grew up
speaking the language they dream in if
you love someone's language truly love
it then you can find a door to their
culture identity and what makes them who
they are and I think that that's been
very hard for me to find because I use
language differently and I communicate a
little a little differently and the few
people who understand that understand
what I mean when I say something it just
opens up a whole new level of
connectedness that it was really hard
for me to achieve and that's actually
all I had planned to say perfect that
was like just under five minutes and
although we're not supposed to yet have
a conversation I just want to say I
really want him to be our prime minister
right I'm not I'm not Canadian but he's
great you know about so would you like
to go Mick or would you like me to go oh
no I just go in order
Wow so how did my autism diagnosis
affect my life how didn't it this is I
mean like can't you spoke to like
figuring it out and sort of having the
answers like I don't know I think a lot
about questions of identity questions of
like like what what is a person who am i
what am I like and I think that one of
the reasons I have spent so much of my
life like pursuing these interesting
philosophical questions and and trying
to like get as good at communication as
I could and trying to like understand
why I'm having a hard time articulating
which I know y'all will understand um
it's kind of like I spent 34 years
taking care of the needs desires and
completely like nonsensical impulses of
like a fake identity that I was wearing
so that I wouldn't get beat up and I
could not see it I was I had a lot of
ablest advice I recognized once I
realized that I myself was autistic I
realized that I was devoting a
non-trivial amount of effort to looking
down on other people that were autistic
but that weren't masking the way that I
was and like I'm not a person who looks
down on people and that always made me
uncomfortable and I couldn't understand
what was going on and it wasn't until I
finally realized like oh I hate myself
and I'm projecting that onto people that
I see that remind me of the parts of
myself that I can't accept and holy
right like how do you get to that point
like I until I
stood that I was autistic I had no
framework to understand the primary
mechanism through which I related to
herself and to the people around me and
getting those answers allowed me to tell
myself a story of Who I am that made
sense for the first time
I can't even articulate to somebody
who's never had that experience like
could you imagine being 34 years old and
like realizing that you're not who you
thought you weren't like you've lived
your whole life like feeling a little
bit a little bit off a little bit wrong
like things things never quite add up
and then you get this answer and this
answer is something that you've probably
been exposed to before in your life and
bounced right off of it because the way
the answer was presented to you is
pathologized
and described in language that like
being autistic is a completely
subjective experience but when you read
about like DSM criteria or like what
other people described or even like
doctors who are like ostensibly experts
you know it's all behavioral and so I
don't know I
I think of us as an invisible dinosaur I
think of us as like we are a people we
have always been a people we have a
culture that is a natural culture that
emerges when we are together and we've
spent thousands of years like trapped
each of us alone each of us not
understanding or seeing that the other
ones are out there and we're living
through a cultural moment where we as a
group are defining our own cultural
identity for kind of the first time in
history and the connections that I feel
the other autistic people people like me
are things that I don't know I went I
went three decades of my life without
ever really being able to have that kind
of a connection and that does things to
you because humans are social animals
and your well-being as a social animal
is contingent like on social integration
and knowing who you are and being seen
and accepted and understood by the
people around you and if you don't have
that then you're not going to be okay
and for me realizing I was autistic
finally gave me the tools try to get
that and it's it's completely changed my
life
it's I'll stop there you're both really
good at this five minute mark it was
like both right under it all right
couple of autistic people to be like
right on time I know it's the same
before you got your cat that I like to
go like right if it's that like is it
counts down because I preached I'm in
I'm like to the second I'm like nobody
gets close to 30 minutes I'm like okay
we got wrap it up got it right on all
right I'll meet both of you so my
journey to self diagnosis was a somewhat
strange one I grew up knowing I was a DD
and as an adult I went in to get some
AED meds because I I'm kind of anti
prescription for myself and the doctor I
had at the time was like well we have to
read iagnosed you which was a weird
feeling so I'm like you're taking away a
part of my identity what do you mean you
have to read iagnosed me and when I was
getting the diagnosis and doing the
checklists there was one that
was like weird I'm like well I'm all of
those things but those aren't EDD and it
was an autism checklist and then I
looked at more of the like female parts
of autism and I'm like this is me these
are my people this is me but I still
didn't again I'd like a formal diagnosis
because of course a formal diagnosis of
autism is much harder than a formal
diagnosis of a DD and actually the the
catalyst was was Nick here had posted a
Twitter thread describing what it was
like to be autistic and I remember
reading it and crying and being like I
am every single one of these things and
again these are my people
this is where I belong and I have a lot
of core comorbid things as well I am a
DD as well I had brain tumors and and
the resulting stuff that happened to get
rid of them and what came out of that
left me with some minor brain damage
that has definitely affected my life so
I have a very neurotypical I'm
neurodivergent minds that both is partly
what I grew up knowing was different
EDD what I grew up with not knowing was
different which was autism and this
actual change in my brain that happened
that gives me so much perspective but on
the diversity that our brains are on
this planet and what that gives us not
just as individuals but as a society
that like that is what we need we need
to have different Minds thinking in
different ways and yet at the same time
we only have access to one window to see
the world from our own brain and so we
don't know if we're different or the
same and that's including the hope in
their own typical people like you don't
know because you only have one to view
so we view out into the world and see
the world from the reflection of our
window and we can't understand what it's
like to live in anyone else's shoes and
I think that's one of the blessings of
autism is being autistic and meeting
other autistic people we know no two
autistic people are this
even though were that same culture that
those same were like we found our people
and yet were not the same and I think
neurotypicals can maybe learn a lot from
that and that I can see I have my own
vision on how we can create a better
world that I am actively working towards
the idea Cafe is a big part of that and
I can see how our diversity not just our
neurodiversity but also our physical
diversity or emotional diversity just
that we have different talents and
challenges is a big piece of how we
create a better world together easily
and effectively once we like tap into
that if the print if like we can find
enough people who are willing to get
over their ableism in all areas then we
can move forward creating a system that
like taps into that taps into our flow
taps into what each of us is here to do
and so the I'm not even answering the
question the impact on my life has been
huge because it clicked a lot of things
into being and I actually already kind
of before even figuring out and
self-diagnose seen I had kind of gotten
over a lot of the that society puts
on you about autism I had kind of gotten
rid of a lot of my mask it's still I'm
still uncovering pieces of it because
it's like put in place from from really
young and there's and like allowing
myself to kind of have meltdowns and
feeling what that's like and feeling
what it's like to be in that body and
like letting go of what society has put
on me is like this is what you do and
this is what you have to be because
there is so much more under that that I
have to give and I think that I don't
think I'm unique I don't think I'm
special in that regard I think all of us
have something amazing underneath our
masks and that includes neurotypical
people like we're all forced to be a
certain way in society our gender our
race our class our you know everything
and when we go underneath that ego but
Who am I that is like where the magic is
and if you have two paths and society
says one and your soul your whatever
your essence says another you should
always be following your essence but
most of us follow Society and I think as
an autistic person I look at one of
other ways I knew I was autistic was
credit throneburg I was like she's me
it's like I was I was like her when I
was little and like exact like no one
else would be doing the climate March
not at that in the 80s but like that was
me and there is a powerful force there
that we need on this planet for us to
burn much I think we're once we get over
a mask once we get we get who we are
we're more easily able to say like eff
society
I'm here to forge my own path and so
it's had a big impact on me and the
world and sorry my five everybody
it's like a society my six-year-old okay
all right that's my five minutes we both
brought up sort of the the the
quote-unquote like female presenting
autism female phenotype of autism which
can I agree with you that the wording is
horrible because it I have that
presentation of autism
I relate much more strongly to female
presentation I was masking from a very
young age I grew up multilingual I grew
up like learning to present to you know
I recently got a formal diagnosis or
formal confirmation of my self diagnosis
and something that the diagnostician
told me was that I was a very
circumstantial person which was an
expression I'd never heard before
thought that made me feel a little bit
inadmissible in court or something but
it turns out that that just means that I
in her judgment it was somebody who
behaved appropriately to the context in
which I find myself and it's like well
obviously that was my entire identity
for most of my life so yeah I'm really
good at that part it's the context where
there's nobody around and I just need to
be with myself and be okay that has
caused me trouble because I know you
know when when you are habituated into
relying on these external markers for
for how you are in the world then
in their absence you don't really know
how to be and that's something I've been
struggling what I don't know what you
it's like I have to give myself
permission to be me and I tell myself
okay you're alone right now and you need
to rock or you need to do that try it
try it see if it works and I have to
verbally tell myself you can do this you
can try this it's okay it's like taking
off the costume brings guilt or
something that's interesting I don't hmm
I've done that try non of um I don't
know but I think it was in the face of
one of the Facebook group someone had
said that they were like flapping their
arms in public and we're like you know I
realize and I was like oh I don't do
that and so I tried it and I was like oh
I don't I do this I like do it this way
I'm like yes I think I'm like oh okay I
did you that actually I've done that my
whole life but it's like a socially
acceptable way and like I definitely
rock and I there's a lot of things I'm
like okay yeah it feels better it feels
better to be able to to do that and
allow it in my body wherever I am but
then there's time so I'm like this is
not appropriate you're not supposed to
be doing this yeah well and I find it's
been a journey because for me I guess I
had always had some stems but I was also
grew up um like I had an abusive
childhood and I was not in my body
essentially I was pretty dissociated my
entire life until relatively recently is
the last two years I had a major
autistic burnout and breakdown um
because I had to deal with a
developmental trauma disorder and so the
last two years has been me figuring out
okay what's an autism thing and what's a
trauma thing and I didn't worry about
the autism things I'm like that's just
time and figuring it out and I can do
that I mean my whole career has been
helping kids figure that out in
themselves I can do that to me and then
figuring out what's a trauma thing which
does need to be like resolved and not a
thing and and stimming was something
that was an interesting journey to
figure out I'm still doing it to figure
out what makes me feel good and I had to
do a lot of work I guess it's called
alexithymia when you're not really aware
of your own sensations and I had
but probably because of both of those
things and so I've done a lot of work
with somatic stuff and trying to just
recognize how does my body feel when I
do this is this better is this worse and
in doing that I have been able to figure
out that there are certain stems that I
really feel like I can probably see the
soyang a little bit and I don't I don't
think many of mine are particularly
overt but I've it's been a process of
being like okay I'm in public and I used
to I guess put on headphones I wouldn't
even be listening to music but I could
sway on the street and the headphones
and people just assumed I was listening
to music and then it dawned on me I
don't have any music on when I do that
that's just me I just realized while you
were talking cat like I have it I have a
six-year-old that when she was an infant
she would be on me and I would be like
swaying constantly and even when she was
off of me I would be swaying like the
amount I was like oh this feels good
tonight that was long before I'm only
connecting the two now and every time I
hold a baby it's like automatic like
that is what we do with babies and it's
so calming and why is it typical person
would find it calming and I mean they've
shown that if you're doing a lot of
trauma stuff even like a swinging motion
a rocking motion people in boats
wonderful for the rocking motion is that
I think a very human comforting thing to
maybe just like the EMDR I've been doing
a lot of trauma therapy - it's the first
thing that has like really helped me I
spend a lot of time doing like trying to
do CBT you know where they teach you to
ignore you're not engaged with your
negative thoughts you know and what I
kind of discovered is that a lot of my
negative thoughts were mic means
screaming out to be met you
using CBT to ignore that was actually
not helping me me neither
the semantics are so have you read about
polyvagal theory Nick Fergus poor
disappoint you I'm gonna write that down
yeah it's so
he's been doing research for decades I
guess and his he has like a slightly
different model of like threat detection
and anxiety and depressions and these
things he basically says traditionally
we think of safety as a property of the
environment right and we like try to
make the environment safe but actually
you know and so we think about like
trying to remove risks right we remove
dangers he says polyvagal theory says
basically like look lizards
you know our lizard brain doesn't have
any social anything its relation to like
other entities is like are you my dinner
or am i your dinner or neither right and
mammals come around and they're social
they need to like raise each other right
they need to like collaborate and so
they needed some way to shut down
actually the lizard brain and polyvagal
theory says that it's not the case that
mammals sometimes feel danger it's the
case that mammals are the first thing
capable of feeling safety when you feel
safe that is an override on your lizard
brain and to the extent that you do not
feel safe your brain is delegating
responsibility to the lizard brain
because the mammal brain is and you
don't have access to it and this is a
completely different way to like look at
trauma because it's you know we have
this word trauma that means so many
things to so many people it's almost
like like autism right it just it it
means like you gots problems and like
yeah like but like what if we really
could like reason about that a little
more formally you know it's pretty cool
to me yeah oh it's weird like like my
it's hard for me to tease apart what
belongs to what part of my you know
sissy's my formal ones and my one is
self diagnosed and that is it because
I'm like I'm allergic to stress like
when I'm under stress it's not that I'm
like I'm a strong person but like I fall
asleep my nervous system shuts down and
so I've had to de-stress my entire life
like just be like nope
gone that's gone that's gone and now
that I'm like at near zero stress as
much as I could be I'm now able to like
add things back in and be like okay that
was a weird rule that I enforced
and but like how important it is and I
have chronic fatigue and I do have it
there are things that aren't quite about
autism but a huge piece of it was autism
burnout was like oh all the sensory
coming at you all day every day and
dealing with other people's emotions is
exhausting and stressful and needing it
like being able to do that without my
mask on slightly easier but it's still
hard and I need a lot of time to be by
myself
these stress did you also have the
experience of like I understand now that
when there's a super loud you know a
siren goes by I'm gonna have like a
negative emotional response to that but
four decades of my life where I didn't
know I was autistic I didn't realize I
had sensitivities I didn't really you
know I just thought oh I just am moody
and get depressed or upset a lot and
like there's no real reason for it you
know it's just my brain chemistry
whatever you know and like now it's like
holy how did I not come like put
together the fact that like the state
that I'm in is a direct result of this
and this and this and this I have
similar in mind is often times delayed
so like if I know like I'll hear sirens
say and then I don't know what I think
about it at first and so by the time the
grumpy comes it's passed and so it took
a long time yeah oh wait okay that it
just took me a few minutes to realize
like my body goes into panic and then if
I don't identify what's going on right
away which is often hard then it gets
into this like scared zone where my mood
goes like later freeze and yeah you
don't listen your legs over delay on it
too right that's the alexithymia it's
like so this is often held up as like a
symptom of autism right like we have
difficulty naming our own emotions but
the other place I always thought that me
also shows up is toxic masculinity like
a lot of men just can't name their own
emotions either to the same extent and
not just because they're like you know
dumb meatheads or whatever it's because
they literally can't and to me what that
says is that Alex emulate their you'd
suggest that Alex Athena is like a
property that emerges when you don't
have the validation of your emotional
state from the people around you right
you experience emotions subjectively but
you don't learn to map your subjective
experience to other people's
presentation you have these two
different every emotion has two parts
and they're not connected very much my
experience yes you're talking about how
realizing you were dissociated from us
to your life I had the same thing I felt
safe for the first time like a couple
years ago and I was like wait what this
is how everyone else is funny
know what you were missing until you
heard it you're like whoa that's weird
too like raising a child whom part of
all stuff on your own autism is I think
that she has a DD but she doesn't have
autism and I'm like oh she has this
piece but no but like there's something
but she is in touch with her emotions
she has taught me because I didn't get
in the way of them I knew enough that I
knew I didn't know how to do that so I
was like oh we're gonna let you do it
we're gonna let you have a tantrum and
she'd be like freaking out and then just
like totally fine a minute later I was
like can I do that anyone I mean I sue I
assume anyone maybe I'm wrong but I like
to assume that anyone can learn this
with time and care and skill and I mean
that's how I did it I know I'm not
everyone um but I like I had also mmm um
I have two kids one of them I'm fairly
certain is not autistic the other one
I'm fairly certain is partly because she
was having what I would see as meltdowns
like I don't cystic meltdown and at a
certain point I was like you know what
I'm not sure but I'm gonna just raise
her and start treating her like she's
autistic and see if that makes a
difference and everything got better um
she very wasn't very rarely now how
house meltdowns mind you she's she's
five so I mean my changes she gets older
in the social pressure gets more but
I've been very like from the start with
both my kids like let's let's be aware
of who we are of what
we're feeling and of how that affects
the people around us that's an important
thing as well which I understood very
well how I affected people around me as
a child um
because I was hyper focused on that
because again I had a mom who was rather
cruel and so it had to be kind I'm
always aware of what was going on with
her but not robbed me of the ability to
be able to to do that for myself and so
I want to make sure that my children
have books that they can do both in his
parents day as possible so we're at the
31 minute mark so to try to keep it to
30 minutes let's wrap up our our
thoughts
Namah closing a closing statement for a
minute and I'll let it go past the 30
minutes now that I'm aware of these
things I can let them go more easily as
low like well I guess I'll do my closing
say but my objection to Authority
I was like oh I like when someone asks
me to do something it's a no and then
I'm like then I can let it be a moment
and be like no it can be a yes okay come
back to me in a bit we'll see I'll allow
that to process and then I'll see my
body says is it yes or is it or now so
that is my closing I'll do my closing
statement um which I'd like to touch on
Shane um we speaking for myself and
speaking for a lot of the people that
I've interacted with as I've been on
this journey like we are taught to be
ashamed of who we are and of the way our
minds and bodies work and anybody who's
listening to this who's struggling with
this I just want to let you know that
that shame is not yours that shame is
something that other people put into you
to make you behave in ways that are more
comfortable for them you don't have to
accept it and a lot of that was put
there when you were a kid and you didn't
know it's okay to put that shame down
and to love who you are and if you're
somebody who's struggling to figure out
how to put down your mask and get in
touch with who you actually are
underneath which is something a lot of
us actually get stuck with my advice to
you is to concentrate on those things
that make you experience feelings of
shame and fear
because those are the parts of yourself
that you were taught to hate and that
shame can become a map to those parts of
yourself that you need to learn to love
yourself a little bit better and it'll
change your life
yeah I think well I guess if I'm lost I
I'll leave it with a bit of a hope that
despite how awful people like us and
people who are different for any reason
have been treated throughout history um
I think that thank you to the Internet
we are a global species now we are
getting information accessible to people
all over the place and when you don't
know that there's a different way you're
stuck and because of this internet
because of things like this like us
doing this right now we're opening
knowledge to people who didn't have it
before we're opening a world that says
hey there's other people like you it
doesn't have to be this way you can find
another way and there are Facebook
groups and there are things and if you
look enough you will find your people so
keep looking if you don't live in a
place where you have your people around
you look online find your people we are
out there you're not alone thank you and
I just want wrap it up for the idea cafe
if anyone is watching and wants to do an
idea Cafe you can contact me at idea
cafe at 20:20 at gmail.com or and this
will all be in the links links down
below but I'm open to doing a idea cafe
on basically any question there might be
ones I can't answer and I will take my
step back and let other people have that
have the floor and and speak and I'll
just facilitate I think this is an
amazing way to connect with other people
and hear other stories and experience
this has been great I've had so much fun
this so I'm gonna stop recording now and
bye to you